<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | Diary of Captain Moroon Cocoon]]></title>
  <link href="http://nhatquang238.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nhatquang238.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-19T02:06:23+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://nhatquang238.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cocoon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Audit Negotiation &amp; Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://nhatquang238.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/audit-negotiation-and-design/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T00:49:08+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://nhatquang238.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/audit-negotiation-and-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>The audit negotiation</h1>

<h2>Preparation in the black-art kingdom</h2>

<p>Before this week&rsquo;s negotiation simulation took place, I spent one day to research on negotiation tactics and decided the best approach to persuade my partner.</p>

<p>Since I had already read the book by Ronald Dawson &ldquo;The secret of power negotiation&rdquo;, I ran through many combinations in my head. I even considered black-art tactics such as initial extreme offer, the long silence, or lessening my partner patience by being an asshole.</p>

<p>However, these tactics failed to materialise because our prof, who &ldquo;happened&rdquo; to collect almost all famous published books about negotiation, &ldquo;happened&rdquo; to tell the whole class about these approaches. So similar to the previous simulation, I went into battle with no concrete plan because what I prepared had all been busted.</p>

<p>The last thing I could count on was my patience. And luckily, I seemed to possess a bit more of that compared to my partner.</p>

<h2>Going into battle. Or is it?</h2>

<p>For this week negotiation, we received a complex one with 8 issues. And if we couldn&rsquo;t agree on ALL 8 terms, we would reach an impasse despite whatever amount of effort we spent. To make matters worse, there was a pre-defined range that we had to succumb to. For example, my goal as a buyer was to get a price as cheap as possible. Yet, there was a cap of $220,000. That meant even if I achieved $210,000, it would still count as a failed term and as such, the contact could not be signed.</p>

<p>I figured out that if I couldn&rsquo;t understand what my partner value, I would never been able to find a leverage to help boost my favourable issues. In order to achieve that, I would need to trust my partner to be a rational negotiator and approach the game with the mindset of finding a common ground for our problem. A typically nice-guy approach isn&rsquo;t it? I thought that it would be easy to implement. Yet, emotion swings bigger than I expected.</p>

<p>I set out by asking her whether she had any preferred issue that she wanted to discuss. But she did not have one and instead through me a very high price of $320,000. The max I could take was $270,000!!! That was way above my range. Hence, I got defensive and we began nitpicking over the audit fee.</p>

<p>I was much more cautious in cooperating with her. What followed was very similar to the coffee negotiation where I tried to decline every concession she gave and insisted on a different open price. We got stuck in that issue for almost 15 mins and we didn&rsquo;t reach a conclusion.</p>

<p>At that moment, my partner started talking about how tiresome this negotiation was. And that stroke me really hard! What had I done?</p>

<h2>Basic user experience strategy: listen to your user</h2>

<p>I stupidly fell into my own trap of playing the mind game too much and forgot about helping her out. I forgot to consider one simple situation that we could have 2 different ranges and therefor lead to her extreme initial offer.</p>

<p>Instead, I thought that she was trying to use the black-art on me! What was more horrible was that I spent 1/3 of the time allowed bargaining over 1 issue in the total 8!!!</p>

<p>I was supposed to be listening to her problem and find out her painful issues. Had I allowed her to talk, we wouldn&rsquo;t have wasted that much time. Had I allowed her to talk, I could align our benefits and reach for a total bigger piece (or a win-win game).</p>

<p>I went back to my root in user experience design and treated the negotiation as a problem finding session. It changed the course of the negotiation to a better path.</p>

<p>I took a deep breath. That helped calming me down a bit. After that, I started telling her what I was most concern about and which issues I could be more lenient. She did become more opened and we quickly reach agreement on 4 issues. These 4 issues later turned out to be compatible issues and integrative issues. We got the best total outcomes for these problems!</p>

<h2>Be patient, m'young lady!</h2>

<p>However, since time started to run out, she became more rushed and lost her calmness (which I believe is the only thing you shouldn&rsquo;t lose during a negotiation!). She looked more nervous and concerned about time than me. Thus, I knew that I could win this by refusing to comply to any of the 4 remaining issues and push these very near to the closing time.</p>

<p>We didn&rsquo;t have a deal when we walked back to class! This meant that we agreed on an impasse, an undesired state, even though my total gained point was above 3000 (my resistance point). I knew that I was greedy but I decided to take the risk since I had always been an adventurous guy.</p>

<p>Thus I made her the final suggestion before we entered the class: I would trade my audit fee (which gave the highest point among the 8 issues and also happened to be her most important issue) for the other 3 issues. Very quickly, I had her agreed on my favorable term for the other 3 issues. The total point gained from the 3 issues was far above the point I lost for the audit fee. This resulted in me arriving at 5800pts and her getting 4600pts. I was on the better side of the deal once again!</p>

<p>I like both negotiation simulations I had until this point because they gave me one hell of a mind challenge. Being able to turn the situation around on your feet is a very excited feeling that I would always dive in.</p>

<p>However, for this audit simulation, I and my partner were 400pts away from the optimal score. That was a bit sad. I could have realised the nature of the game, a win-win one, earlier and wouldn&rsquo;t waste 15 mins. That would give me more time to set up and discuss over integrative terms.</p>

<h2>Overall assessment</h2>

<h3>My strength</h3>

<p>More patient than my partner, especially towards the end of the negotiation.</p>

<h3>My weakness</h3>

<p>React too quickly to negative responds. I should let them sink down.</p>

<h3>Partner&rsquo;s strength</h3>

<p>Focus really strong on her most important issue: audit fee. Use good reasons to back up her concessions or quoted terms.</p>

<h3>Partner&rsquo;s weakness</h3>

<p>Less patient. Reveal too much of that through body language and verbal expression.</p>

<h2>On the similarity of negotiation and design</h2>

<p>During the debrief, my prof mentioned something really fascinating:</p>

<blockquote><p>That things could be very complex but easy and those seemed simple could be immensely hard to get right.</p></blockquote>

<p>This idea synchronise with me strongly since it is the basic motto in design that I&rsquo;ve practiced for quite awhile:</p>

<blockquote><p>Achieving simplicity without losing context.</p></blockquote>

<p>In fact, it is quite common to see &ldquo;designers&rdquo; and product makers jam a bunch of functions into their applications. Imagine Photoshop or Microsoft Powerpoint and you will get my point. Those are very polished and complex applications. It&rsquo;s easier to put both functions into a design instead of killing one. But that doesn&rsquo;t make a product better. It makes the product more complex. And most of the time confusing to beginners.</p>

<p>Negotiation is the same. Between the 2 simulations, I believe the audit negotiation is more complex with 8 problems but easier to &ldquo;get away&rdquo; since you can trade off issues. So negotiators are generally happier because they can tell their boss that even they don&rsquo;t get the price right, they achieve &ldquo;some other terms&rdquo;.</p>

<p>However, for this type of integrative negotiation, it&rsquo;s harder to reach a win-win situation, which, to me, is the only true win when you play this game. Reaching a win-win situation enlarges the total piece for both parties and allow them to walk away with a good relationship.</p>

<p>To be able to achieve win-win, you got to be really understanding and listening to your partners. But that&rsquo;s easier talk than done since we all have our ego. I almost lost the big picture during my audit negotiation!</p>

<p>And when you reduce the number of terms you negotiate for, the whole game becomes simpler since you only have a few terms to focus on. However, as seen with the coffee simulation, it&rsquo;s harder for negotiators since they are fighting over scarer resources with lesser trade-offs available.</p>

<blockquote><p>The best strategy is only achieved if you know what game you are playing.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
